雅可比矩阵中有很多非常丰富的信息，我们可以将其用作
There is a lot of really rich information in the Jacobian matrix and we can use it as
一种诊断工具，用于处理机器人在特定关节角度配置下的移动情况。
a sort of diagnostic tool to work at how well the robot can move at a particular joint angle configuration.
让我们更详细地研究雅可比矩阵是奇异的情况，这是
Let us look in more detail at the case where the Jacobian matrix is singular and this is
Jacobian矩阵对于这里所示姿势的机器人来说是什么样的，其中是关节
what the Jacobian matrix looks like for a robot in the pose shown here, where joint
角度五等于零。给出了由于关节4引起的末端执行器的运动
angle five is equal to zero. The motion of the end-effector due to joint four is given
由雅可比矩阵的这一列和由于关节引起的末端执行器的运动
by this column of the Jacobian matrix and the motion of the end-effector due to joint
雅可比矩阵的这一列给出了六个。
six is given by this column of the Jacobian matrix.
您会注意到这两列是相同的，这意味着它们会产生
You will notice that these two columns are identical and that means that they result
在相同的末端执行器运动中，在这种特殊情况下，它是围绕世界的旋转
in the same end-effector motion and in this particular case it is rotation about the world
Z轴。我们可以通过改变联合四或改变联合六来获得相同的动作。
Z axis. We can get the same motion by changing joint four or by changing joint six.
对于方阵，如果两列相同，则它变为单数;和一位数学家
For a square matrix, if two columns are identical, then it becomes singular; and a mathematician
会说矩阵的等级从完全等级，等级6降低到等级5。
would say that the rank of the matrix has reduced from full rank, rank six, to a rank of five.
这是MATLAB中相同的雅可比矩阵，我们可以清楚地看到第四列和第四列
Here is that same Jacobian matrix in MATLAB and we can clearly see that columns four and
第六列是相同的。如果我们计算矩阵的确定性，我们就会看到它
column six are identical. If we compute the determinate of the matrix, we see that it
等于零;这意味着雅各比派是单数的。如果我计算这个等级
is equal to zero; it means that this Jacobian is singular. If I compute the rank of this
矩阵，它等于五，这就是说，只有五个唯一列
matrix, it is equal to five and that’s saying that there are only five unique columns in
这个矩阵。其中两列完全相同。
this matrix. Two of the columns are identically equal.
现在让我们看一下更健康的雅可比矩阵。我们要计算雅可比行列式
Let us look now at a more healthy Jacobian matrix. We are going to compute the Jacobian
对于设定的关节角度Qn。该矩阵没有明显的重复列。它的决定因素
for the set joint angle Qn. This matrix has no obvious duplicated columns. Its determinant
不等于零，其等级等于六。这意味着所有六列都是唯一的。
is not equal to zero and its rank is equal to six. That means that all six columns are unique.
在上一个讲座中，我们介绍了速度椭圆的概念，我们这样做了
In the last lecture, we introduced the concept of the velocity ellipse and we did this in
两个维度。对于一组位于所有平面上的圆上的关节角度
two dimensions. For a set of joint angles which lie on a circle in the plane of all
可能的关节角速度，我们将其映射到所有可能的空间中的椭圆
possible joint angle velocities, we mapped that into an ellipse in the space of all possible
末端效应器速度，表明在特定的机器人关节角度配置，
end-effector velocities and that indicated that in a particular robot joint angle configuration,
机器人能够在世界Y方向上移动得比它可以移动得更快
the robot was able to move more quickly in the world Y direction than it could move in
世界X方向。我们可以为六轴机器人做同样的事情，但数学
the world X direction. We can do the same thing for a six-axis robot, but the mathematics
有点复杂。
is a little bit more complex.
我们在机器人末端执行器空间速度和关节之间存在这种关系
We have this relationship between the robot end-effector spatial velocity and the joint
角速度。我可以将这两个方程结合起来，得出这个表达式
angle velocity. I can combine these two equations and come up with this expression which is
六维超椭球或椭圆的方程;所以它有点儿
the equation for a hyper-ellipsoid or some ellipse in six dimensions; so it is a little
很难理解你的头脑。大多数情况下，我们对前三个要素感兴趣
hard to get your head around. Mostly, we are interested in the first three elements
空间速度;这就是机器人末端执行器的平移速度。
of the spatial velocity; that is the translational velocity of the robot end-effector.
在这种情况下，我们最终得到一个三维椭球，我们可以很容易地绘制。所以，
In this case, we end up with a three-dimensional ellipsoid which we can quite easily plot. So,
这是特定配置中机器人的速度椭圆体。我们可以看
here is the velocity ellipsoid for a robot in a particular configuration. We could view
从不同角度看这个椭球，我们可以看到椭圆很长
this ellipsoid from different angles and we could see that the ellipse is quite elongated
在垂直方向上，它在朝向基座的方向上相当平坦
in the vertical direction and it is reasonably flat in the direction towards the base of
机器人，所以机器人能够在长的方向上最快速地移动
the robot and so the robot is able to move most quickly in the direction of the long
椭圆的轴线在短轴方向上移动得慢得多
axis of the ellipse and it moves much more slowly in the direction of the short axis
这个椭圆体。
of this ellipsoid.
如果椭球实际上是一个球体，那么我们说运动是各向同性的;这意味着
If the ellipsoid was actually a sphere, then we say the motion is isotropic; that means
机器人末端执行器能够在任何方向上快速移动。这很方便
that the robot end-effector is able to move equally quickly in any direction. It is convenient
引入可操作性的概念，这是一个难以理解的词，它是一个简单的标量度量
to introduce a notion of manipulability, a difficult word to say, and it is a simple scalar measure
这说明了速度椭圆体的形状。如果可操纵性相等
that says something about the shape of the velocity ellipsoid. If manipulability is equal
到一，然后我们有各向同性运动的情况;机器人能够平等移动
to one, then we have the case of isotropic motion; the robot is able to move equally
任何方向都快。
fast in any direction.
如果可操纵性等于零，则椭圆体会折叠并变为刚好
If manipulability is equal to zero, then the ellipsoid is collapsed and it becomes just
椭圆形板，这意味着不可能在一个笛卡尔方向上运动
an elliptical plate and it means that motion in one Cartesian direction is not possible
一点都不通常，可操纵性将介于0和1之间。如果是
at all. In general, the manipulability will be somewhere between zero and one. If it is
接近一，这意味着机器人被配置为在其工作空间的任何方向上快速移动。
close to one, it means that the robot is configured to move quite quickly in any direction in its workspace.
随着可操纵性接近于零，这意味着机器人处于尴尬的姿势
As the manipulability gets closer to zero, it means that the robot is in an awkward pose
并且有一些方向根本无法快速移动。操作性
and there are some directions where it was not able to move very quickly at all. Manipulability
是机器人关节角度的强大功能，因此根据任务，您可能需要
is a strong function of the robot joint angles, so depending on the task, you may need to
设置机器人关节角度，使其达到所需的速度，以实现该特定任务。
set the robot joint angles so that it has got the speed required in order to achieve that particular task.
我们将使用MATLAB显示其中一个速度椭圆体。第一件事
We are going to use MATLAB to display one of these velocity ellipsoids. The first thing
我要做的是将机器人绘制在中间的关节角度配置中
I am going to do is to plot the robot in the joint angle configuration that is in the middle
它的工作空间，这就是机器人的样子，然后我将使用它
of its work-space and that is what the robot looks like and then I am going to use the
椭圆叠加在速度椭球上的方法。
method for ellipse to overlay on that a velocity ellipsoid.
这个方法有很多参数和选项。首先，我通过联合
This method has got quite a number of arguments and options. First of all, I pass in the joint
我感兴趣的角度。我想要将椭圆绘制成蓝色和
angles that I am interested in. I want the ellipse to be plotted in the colour blue and
我希望椭圆上的边线为白色。我想要整个事情
I want the edge lines on the ellipse to be in white. I want the whole thing to
有些半透明，所以我要给它一个0.5的alpha值，然后我们
be somewhat translucent, so I am going to give it an alpha value of 0.5 and there we
看速度椭圆。
see the velocity ellipse.
现在，我可以旋转它，从各种不同的方向看它
Now, I can rotate this around and look at it from all sorts of different orientations
和观点。如果我一边看它，我们可以看到椭圆是相对的
and viewpoints. If I look at it pretty much side on, we can see that the ellipse is relatively
在朝向机器人基座的方向上变薄。那是机器人的方向
thin in the direction toward the base of the robot. That is the direction where the robot
不能快速移动或在垂直Z方向移动，基本上是向上和
is not able to move very quickly or as in the vertical Z direction, basically up and
向下，机器人能够很快地移动;这就是速度椭圆体
down, the robot is able to move quite quickly; so that is the velocity ellipsoid for this
关节角度配置。
joint angle configuration.
如果我选择不同的关节角度配置，这就是机器人手臂向右伸展的位置
If I choose a different joint angle configuration, this is where the robot arm is stretched right
在我的工作空间中，水平，即关节角度矢量Qs，然后是机器人
out horizontally which is the joint angle vector, Qs, in my workspace then the robot
在那个配置中，现在我将绘制这个特定配置的椭圆，
is in that configuration and now I am going to plot the ellipse for this particular configuration,
所以我会回来编辑这个命令，将Qn改为Qs，这里我们有速度
so I would just come back and edit this command, change Qn to Qs, and here we have the velocity
这种特殊情况的椭圆体。
ellipsoid for this particular case.
现在，我们可以看到它是一个椭圆;但一边说，它根本没有厚度，它
Now, we can see that it is an ellipse; but side on, it has got no thickness at all, it
是一个盘子。因此，在这种特定的关节角度配置中，机器人能够移动它
is a plate. So, in this particular joint angle configuration, the robot is able to move its
来自这个特殊视图的末端效应器上下左右;但看着它
end-effector from this particular view up and down and left and right; but looking it
通过这种方式，它根本无法将末端执行器移回基座。
at this way, it has got no ability at all to move the end-effector back towards the base.